<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discovery of the priests, that say they are sent off by the Lord, but upon trial are found out of the commands of Christ, the prophets, and Apostles, and to be those that are not sent of the Lord, but to be such that the sent ones of the Lord did cry wo against, and to be such that are false apostles, deceitful, wicked, transforming themselves into the apostles of Christ: and no marvail, for Satan himself is transformed into an angel of light; therefore it is no great thing, if his ministers be transformed as the ministers of righteousness, ... With a few words to such professors and prophane, that together joyn to persecute the righteous: and to the ranters that do commit all manner of sins with greediness. Darkness denied by the children of Light, and the babe of Christ growing up to a perfect man. / Written from one who is known to the world by the name of John Pain, who accounts it great riches to suffer reproaches, and afflictions with the people of the Lord, who scornfully by the world are called Quakers, ... Written from Starford in Hartford-shire the 7. day of the 4. month. 1655.</title>
            <author>Pain, John, shoemaker.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 113 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90622</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P188</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E848_22</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203094</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863174</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863174</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115359</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90622)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115359)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 128:E848[22])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discovery of the priests, that say they are sent off by the Lord, but upon trial are found out of the commands of Christ, the prophets, and Apostles, and to be those that are not sent of the Lord, but to be such that the sent ones of the Lord did cry wo against, and to be such that are false apostles, deceitful, wicked, transforming themselves into the apostles of Christ: and no marvail, for Satan himself is transformed into an angel of light; therefore it is no great thing, if his ministers be transformed as the ministers of righteousness, ... With a few words to such professors and prophane, that together joyn to persecute the righteous: and to the ranters that do commit all manner of sins with greediness. Darkness denied by the children of Light, and the babe of Christ growing up to a perfect man. / Written from one who is known to the world by the name of John Pain, who accounts it great riches to suffer reproaches, and afflictions with the people of the Lord, who scornfully by the world are called Quakers, ... Written from Starford in Hartford-shire the 7. day of the 4. month. 1655.</title>
                  <author>Pain, John, shoemaker.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22, 31-38, 31-37, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Jo. Streater for Giles Calvert at the Black-spread-Eagle at the end of Paul's,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July. 20.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115359:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOVERY OF THE PRIESTS;</p>
            <p>That ſay they are ſent off by the Lord, but upon trial are found out of the commands of Chriſt, the Prophets, and Apoſtles, and to be thoſe that are not the ſent of the Lord, but to be ſuch that the ſent ones of the Lord did cry wo againſt, and to be ſuch that are falſe Apoſtles, deceitful, wicked, transforming themſelves into the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles of Chriſt: and no marvail, for Satan himſelf is transformed into an Angel of light; therefore it is no great thing, if his miniſters be transformed as the Miniſters of righteouſneſs, whoſe End ſhall be according to their works, for by their works you may know them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> verſes 13, 14, 15. With a few words to ſuch profeſſors and prophane, that together joyn to perſecute the Righteous: and to the Ranters that do commit all manner of ſins with greedineſs. Darkneſs denied by the children of Light, and the Babe of Chriſt growing up to a perfect man.</p>
            <p>Written from one who is known to the world by the name of <hi>John Pain,</hi> who accounts it great riches to ſuffer reproaches, and afflictions with the people of the Lord, who ſcornfully by the world are called <hi>Quakers, Heb.</hi> 12.21. Whom the Devil hath caſt ſome of them into priſon, that they may be tried, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10. But draw neer hither ye ſons of the ſorcereſs, the ſeed of the adulterer and the whore, againſt whom do ye ſport your ſelves, againſt whom do ye make a wrie mouth, and draw the tongue? are ye not children of tranſgreſſion, a ſeed of falſhood, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.3, 4. Ye ſhall leave your name for a curſe to my choſen, the Lord ſhal ſlay thee, and call his people by another name, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.15.</p>
            <p>Reader I would deſire thee to read the proofs that are quoted in this book: Prove all things hold faſt that which is good, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written from</hi> Starford <hi>in</hi> Hartford-ſhire <hi>the</hi> 7. <hi>day of the</hi> 4. <hi>Month.</hi> 1655.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Jo. Streater</hi> for <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the <hi>Black-ſpread-Eagle</hi> at the end of <hi>Paul</hi>'s, 165<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:115359:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115359:2"/>
            <head>A Diſcovery of the Prieſts.</head>
            <p>THE Word of the Lord to you that call your ſelves Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Lord, and ſent by the Lord, but you are not in the obedience of the Lord, if you were the ſent ones of the Lord: and came in the name of the Lord, then would you obey the commands of the Lord; Chriſt ſaith, be not ye called maſters of man, nor call ye man maſter; for one is your maſter even Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.10</note> and he that is greateſt amongſt you, let him be your ſervant. This pride was forbid by him that was lowly, and did waſh the feet of his Diſciples, leaving them an example for to follow, and no man was to follow them no further then they did follow Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now conſider, you that do think this a ſmal matter, and do make a ſlight thing of the command of Chriſt: was not that Chriſt the true Prophet that all men were to hear and obey; and thoſe that do not obey this Prophet, is to be cut off from amongſt his people? is not this one command that you are to obey, and whether not obeying this command, being not called of men Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, be not the ſame command as it was when it was gave forth? Surely it is, why not then obeyed, the Lord in giving that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, did know what he ſpake, and to what he ſpake, though by proud ones it is ſlighted. But know proud fleſh, againſt thee was this command gave forth, though by thee it is ſlighted, but whoſoever doth break one of the leaſt of the commands of Chriſt, is guilty of them all.</p>
            <p>Did ever the commands of Chriſt, and the Miniſters of Chriſt differ before man came to be exalted, but now that which doth ſtand directly againſt the pride of man is not regarded. But wo be to you that breaks one of the leaſt of Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and teach men ſo to do, you ſhall be called the leaſt in the kingdom of Heaven; but that maſterſhip which the Lord hath commanded, do I own, Servants be obedient to your maſters in the Lord, but for ſervants to be called maſters, this is diſowned by Chriſt, and thoſe that do obey Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now conſider if the Miniſters of Chriſt be not called the Lords ſervants and ſervants of men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> what is a ſteward but a ſervant? what is an Ambaſſador but a ſervant? what is a meſſenger but a ſervant?</p>
            <p>Now conſider, are not the Miniſters of Chriſt ſo called in the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115359:3"/>Scripture are they called maſters: but this is no great matter, will you ſay, this is but a civil thing, &amp; you ſay, you do not regard it, but that men wil call you ſo. Nay, it is no civil thing, but a thing that is uncivil, to break the commands of Chriſt. But, the maſterſhip that men do put upon us, is for our Learning, and the Degrees which we did take at the Univerſities, when we did commence Maſters of Arts. This I have heard pleaded both by Prieſts and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>people; ſee now what fountains theſe ſtreams of pride flow from, but the Lord God of power will dry up thoſe Fountaines, that do iſſue forth ſtreams againſt his commands, under what pretence ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, he will famiſh all the gods of the heathen.</p>
            <p>Conſider this both Prieſt and people. Will this ſtand you in ſtead when the Lord ſhall come to plead with all fleſh by his ſword and by his fire; no, it will not ſtand you in ſtead, then obedience will be better then ſacrifices, and rebellion the ſin of witchcraft. Are you not here out of Chriſts doctrine? have you not here obeyed man and not God? doth not the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> ſay in his 2 Epiſtle, <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. that whoſoever tranſgreſſeth, and abideth not in the Doctrine of Chriſt hath not God. When did you ever declare againſt the breach of this Command? no, no, your pride will not ſuffer you to cry down your worldly honor. When did you ever reprove any of your hearers of whom you have a living, &amp; forbid them, calling of you maſters? now if you are maſters, why do you not provide for your ſervants, and not the ſervants for the Maſters? if you be fathers, why do you not provide for your children, and not the chil-for their fathers?<note place="margin">Mat. <hi>23.9.</hi> This is that which Chriſt forbids when he ſaith, call no man fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon the earth.</note> They are not onely called maſters by thoſe that do provide for them, and called fathers by thoſe that were never begotten into the truth by them, but theſe honors they take to themſelves calling one another learned Fathers and Maſters, and receive honor one of another, &amp; not the honor that doth come from the Lord: thoſe that are his ſent ones, are ſtewards and meſſengers and ambaſſadors, which is Honor of the Lords own giving: but for Doctors and Maſters and ſuch like, is honor of the worlds giving, and therefore owned by them, becauſe they are of the world, but thoſe that Miniſtry for Chriſt, theſe things do deny, and againſt it teſtifie,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.4</note> knowing it is better to obey God then man, but this is their many Crowns that the man of ſin who ſitteth in the temple of God, and is exalted above the commands of God, hath put upon their heads to make them ſeem glorious in the eyes of the world, and the world wonders after them; and the world fights for them, when the Lord doth ſend any to cry againſt their deceits by their hearers; and they are perſecuted, torn and rent by the heathen: be aſhamed for ever that ſuch things ſhould be done by you or your hearers; but now is the Lord God of power bringing forth his Miniſtry, and hath brought many forth, praiſed be his name for ever that do obey his commands, which are taught onely
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115359:3"/>by him, and led into the truth which are not made by man, nor by the will of man, but by Jeſus Chriſt, which did aſcend on high for to beget them for the work of the Miniſtery, for the edifying of the body, while they come to a perfect man in Chriſt Jeſus, whoſe ſufficiency is of God that hath made them able Miniſters, not of the Letter but of the ſpirit, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. ſtanding out of the will of man, leading people up to the Lord out of the world or fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with the world; and therefore hated by them, perſecuted and ſcoffed by them; and made the off-ſcouring of the world, of whom the world is not worthy, which doth not receive friendſhip of the world: but ſcornings, ſtockings, and ſtonings, and all manner of reviling, both by prophane and by profeſſors, that ſay they are not of the world, but thoſe that ſay they are not of the world, and yet walk in theſe fruits of darkneſs, they lye and do not ſay the truth. If any man ſeem to be Religious, and cannot bridle his tongue from railing and evil ſpeaking; that mans Religion is vain, let him profeſs what he will.</p>
            <p>Now conſider this, profeſſors and prophane, who joyn together to perſecute the righteous; is this the ſpirit of the Lord, or the ſpirit of the devil, which would if he could, murther all that do profeſs Jeſus. When the man childe is brought forth, doth not the devil ſtand ready to devour it, ſending his floods after it. I charge you in the name of the Lord, joyn not with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane people, but come from amongſt them, for the Lord will be a Sanctuary to his people, for a rock of offence to both houſes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for a gin, for a ſnare to the inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and many amongſt them ſhall ſtumble and fall, and be broken, and be ſnared, and be taken.</p>
            <p>Conſider this you that are profeſſors, it is not for you to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the Lord a way for him to manifeſt his own glory by, leſt you ſtumble, fall, and be broken, be ſnared and taken. Who art thou proud fleſh that wouldſt limit the holy one of Iſrael, to make himſelf manifeſt by: the Lord will chuſe his own laborers to work in his own vineyard: therefore ſilence fleſh and deceit.</p>
            <p>Stop thy mouth for ever, leſt thou be found a fighter againſt the Lord, it will be hard for thee to kick againſt the pricks: behold ſaith the Lord, I and my children are for ſigns and wonders in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> from the Lord of hoaſts that dwelleth in mount <hi>Sion:</hi> hath it not been the portion of the true meſſengers of the Lord in all ages to ſuffer perſecution from the world, yea not onely from the world but by thoſe that in profeſſion were taken out of the world. Were there not honorable and devour women that did ſtir up perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution againſt the Apoſtles?</p>
            <p>Now conſider it is not a profeſſion of the truth that wil keep men and women from joyning with the world, and being one with the world, nay it will not; there is a worldly Religion, they can mock
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115359:4"/>and ſcoff and ſcorn,<note place="margin">Act. 13.50</note> jeer and jeſt, be wanton and proud and heady and high minded, having got the form but perſecute the power, where it is made manifeſt, but the pure Religion they do not know which is unſpotted of the world which doth keep the heart pure out of the defilement up to the Lord,<note place="margin">Jam. 3.13, 15, 16.</note> in lolineſs, in love, which as pure, and brings forth fruits of purity, as love, meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, gentleneſs, not eaſily provoked, but beareth all things: but where there is bitter enveying and ſtrife in your hearts;<note place="margin">Rom. 9.4, 5.</note> glory not and lye not againſt the truth; this wiſdom deſcendeth not from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, but is earthly ſenſual and deviliſh, for where envy and ſtrife is there is confuſion, and every evil work, but the wiſdom that is from above is firſt pure then peacable, gentle, and eaſie to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated, full of mercy and good fruits, without partiality, without hypocriſie: had not the Jews a very high profeſſion? did not they ſay they were <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, and that God was their father and that they were in bondage to no man, and for priviledges and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances none like them who were Iſraelites, to whom did pertain the adoption and glory, and the covenants, and the giving of the law, and the ſervice of God and the promiſes whoſe are the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and of whom as concerning the fleſh Chriſt came who is over all, God bleſſed for ever.</p>
            <p>Theſe are very high priviledges, as any of you Churches doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, but did this keep them from crucifying the Lord of glory? no it did not, therefore take heed how you ſtand leſt you fall, all works that are not wrought in God though it be in the higheſt profeſſion cannot free men from the ſpirit of perſecution, the ſame ſpirit that doth act in the higheſt wickedneſs, it is one with, and of that ſpirit that doth act in the higheſt form of godlineſs, where the light and power is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yea it is the ſame and far more dangerous, for the poor hath been all along perſecuted by it: this is the transformings of the devil into an angel of light, let Prieſts and people ſay what they can; what a ſpirit of perſecution is ſound, it is not of God, it is the fruits of the devil, let it be under what pretence ſoever as I know he hath many to hide his perſecution with, the root is bitter and ſo are the fruits; therefore as you do tender the good of your own ſouls which are precious, do not go on in theſe practices, but ſay you had warning; for the righteous God will judge and reprove with equity: for the meek of the earth he ſhall inherit the earth; with the word of his mouth and with the breath of his lips ſhall he ſlay the wicked: the Lord will puniſh the world for their evil and the wicked for their iniquity, and will cauſe the arrogancy of the proud to ceaſe, and will lay low the haughtineſs of the terrible.</p>
            <p>Conſider this all ſorts of people high and low, rich and poor, it doth concern you all, the hand of the Lord is lifted up againſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115359:4"/>all drunkards and whoremaſters, idolaters, covetuous, oppreſſors, and perſecuters, liars, proud ones, ſcoffers and ſcorners, ſons of <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> ſons of the bondwoman, yea the ſinners in <hi>Sion</hi> ſhall mourn fear ſhall ſurpriſe the hypocrite, therefore think not the word of the Lord ſtrange in theſe our dayes, it is that I have prayed for, it is that I did believe would come, and now my eyes hath ſeen and my heart hath felt the power of the Lord; ye the enemies that are now againſt it have prayed for it, which of you but have pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for it: which of you but have prayed, <hi>Thy Kingdom come,</hi> but now it is coming, you ſpeak all manner of evil of it.<note place="margin">Mat. 24.29, 30, 31, 32, 33.</note> Know the day of your viſitation, for it is ſuch a work of power that doth break down the earth, that nothing ſhall ſtand but that which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſhaken, that his will may be done on earth as it is in heaven perfectly. The Lord is now coming to ſhut the ſeeing eye, and to open the blind eye. Is not now the time that the ſpirit of a deep ſleep hath cloſed the eyes of the prophets; although the ſigns of Chriſts coming the ſecond time without ſin into the world be made manifeſt, yet they ſee it not: Is not the viſion of all become as a ſealed book? is not the Lord turning <hi>Leabnon</hi> into a fruitful field,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.49, 51, 52.53.56.</note> and the fruitful field into a Forreſt, and they know it not. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider where you are, are you not like thoſe that dream that you are ſatisfied, and behold you are empty? is not night upon you, that you cannot ſee the wonders of the Lord which he doth now make manifeſt? but, what is manifeſt amongſt you; fruites of perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, fruites of pride, fruits of covetuouſneſs, theſe fruits of the fleſh are made manifeſt.</p>
            <p>O repent, return to your firſt husband, for theſe are the fruites of the adulterer, and the whoregoing from the light into dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>Return, return, to the light in your conſciences that doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of ſin, that doth diſcover the thoughts &amp; intents of the heart; this light is pure and leads into purity and holineſs.<note place="margin">Iſa. 29.13, 14.</note> Hath not the Lord been a long time drawn nigh to with the lip, when the heart is far from him. Hath not the fear towards him been taught by the precepts of man? therefore behold, ſaith the Lord, I will do a marvellous work and a wonder, the wiſeman ſhall periſh, and the underſtanding of the prudent ſhall be hid, but the deaf ſhall hear, and the eye of the blind ſhall ſee out of obſcurity: now is this promiſe fulfilled, and fulfilling; and now hath the Lord choſe Paſtors according to his own heart, that ſhall feed his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with knowledge according to his promiſe.</p>
            <p>Now is the day of the Lord that he hath ſent forth his meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers as Lambes amongſt the Wolves, counting not their lives too dear to fulfill the work, the Lord hath ſent them forth to do, but leaving all for Chriſts houſe, that durſt not be diſobedient o the call of the Lord, nor conſult with fleſh,<note place="margin">Gal. 1.16.</note> which would
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115359:5"/>ſave it ſelf, but many leaving father and mother, lands and livings, wife and children for love of the pretious ſeed of God that is kept in bondage, groaning for deliverance, and many a one through the Miniſtry of the Lord in them can witneſs a living ſoul redeemed out of death, to praiſe the living Lord; are not theſe the ſigns of the true Miniſtery of Chriſt when the Apoſtles were counted deceivers by the falſe Apoſtles and the reſt, ſome that were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors.</p>
            <p>How did he clear himſelf when they did ſeek a proof of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery? He ſaith in you ward I was not weak, but is mighty in you: this mighty power many hundreds can witneſs, bringing down their high thoughts and words to the obedience, of Jeſus Chriſt: many drunkards and ſwearers, many formal profeſſors, many high flown notioniſts, are brought to the obedience of the croſs which hath crucified them to the world and the world to them: this is the proof of the deſpiſed Miniſtry which is deſpiſed of the world, but owned by thoſe more deare then their lives that doth imbrace it; for thoſe that are joyned to the Lord by their Miniſtery received from the Lord, are Epiſtles write in one anothers heart, this leads into unity, this leads into honor in that which is pure; every member in the body ſerving one another in love, watching one o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the other, the ſtrong bearing with the weak; and here is no rent &amp; ſchiſme, but every one in their meaſures growing up to the father of lights who doth make his all of one heart and one minde they have fellowſhip one with the other in that which is not of the world, but leads out of the world up to God, leads into the light of God; therefore ſilence you enemies, ſtand ſtill in the light of Chriſt which will crucifie you to the world, and the world to you, and you ſhall ſee the ſalvation of the Lord as many a one hath done: praiſes, praiſes be to the Lord for ever.</p>
            <p>Friends conſider the wonderful works of the Lord, be not deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſers and wonderers, and periſh, but know the Lord will do his own work by his own Inſtruments though never ſo deſpiſed: for the preaching of the croſs to them that periſh is fooliſhnes, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us which are ſaved, it is the power of God. The Jews do require a ſign, &amp; the <hi>Greeks</hi> ſeek after wiſdom, but we preach Chriſt crucified, unto the Jews a ſtumbling block, and unto the Greeks fooliſhneſs; the Jews had thoughts that the Lord would have choſen the great and mighty, and the honorable of the world, the learned Scribes and Phariſees, and that he would advance an earthly Kingdom, but did the Lord chuſe ſuch? no, but poor Fiſhermen, Herdſmen, and Tradeſmen, and men unlearned, as <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> were. The ſame. Chriſt is now as ever, and did aſcend on high to give giſts unto men, for the work of the Miniſtry, and this is to laſt to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115359:5"/>
And who art thou proud fleſh, that would limit the Holy one of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> doth not the winde blow where it liſteth? doth the ſpirit of truth that leads into all truth, and knows things to come, confine it ſelfe to one particular ſort of men? no, know it doth not, the Lord hath made himſelf manifeſt, and hath diſcovered that falſe ſpirit: there hath been much contending about the call of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, and writing and preaching one againſt the other, all like <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> loving to have preheminence; but now hath the Lord fully ended that controverſie. But the world will not ſee it, but they ſhall at laſt own it, and they ſhall know,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.9, 10.</note> The wind blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth where it liſteth; but you Prieſts, how little hath this winde blown upon your Garden for this many years, that the ſpices thereof flow out.</p>
            <p>Can you beloved, as you ſay, come into his Garden, and eat his pleaſant fruits? Are not the Grapes of his Vineyard, devoured by the Foxes?</p>
            <p>What fruits are brought forth to God? is not fruits of pride, and fruits of covetouſneſs, reviling, ſcoffing, and ſcorning.</p>
            <p>Now the Lord comes to his Vineyard, doth not theſe fruits ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear both in teacher and hearers: was it not high time to let his Vineyard to more faithful laborers, that it may bring forth fruit to himſelf, for now it is over grown with brambles, and briars fit for the fire: houle ye vine-dreſſers, now the Lord is come to his Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, their fruits are made manifeſt, it is juſt with the Lord, to rain no more rain upon it: what could the Lord have done more then he hath done? but in ſtead of bringing forth good grapes, it hath brought forth wilde Grapes, fruits to your ſelves, not to the Lord, every one ſeeking your own things, and not the things of Chriſt: therefore thus ſaith the Lord, An evil, an onely evil,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exek.</hi> 7.5, to 11.</note> be hold is come, an end is come, the end is come, it watcheth for you, behold it is come, the morning is come upon thee.</p>
            <p>O thou that dwelleſt in the land, the time is come, the day of trouble is neer; now will I ſhortly pour out my fury upon thee, and accompliſh my anger upon thee, and will judge thee according to thy wayes, and will recompence thee for all thy abominations and my eye ſhall not ſpare, neither will I have pity, I will recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence thee according to thy wayes, and the abominations that are in the of midſt thee, and ye ſhall know that I am the Lord that ſmiteth.</p>
            <p>Behold the day it is come, the morning is gone forth, the rod hath bloſſomed, pride hath budded, violence is riſen up into a rod of wickedneſs, none of them ſhall remain nor of their multitudes, neither ſhall their be wailing for them: is not the rod bloſſomed? is not pride budded, is not violence riſe up into a rod of wickednes. Yea pride is not onely buded but it bloſſomed, and that amongſt you that are teachers. Do not you and your wife and children ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115359:6"/>in it that the eyes of all are upon you, ſome wondering at it, moſt following you for it, learning it of you.</p>
            <p>Thus prophaneneſs is gone forth from you, theſe are the fruites they gather from you, fruits of covetuouſneſs and oppreſſion, that is become a proverb in <hi>England: Who more proud then the prieſts, who more covetuous then they?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh for ſhame,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.5. and 8.</note> for ſhame give over. Are you fit to rule the Church of Chriſt, that cannot rule your ſelves and your Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; no, no, ſuch as ruled the Church of Chriſt, they were not greedy of filthy lucre, they were no proud ones, they were no covetous ones, no, but againſt it did teſtifie and ſaid, Let not covetouſneſs be ſo much as once named amongſt you. But tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and anguiſh upon every ſoul of man that doth evil, to the Jew firſt, and alſo to the Gentile; But are not theſe fruits amongſt you? are not you them that profeſs Chriſt in words, but in works do deny him? what have you to do to take the name of the Lord into your mouthes, and will not be reformed? ſhould not every one that doth name the name of Chriſt, depart from iniquity? thou therefore that teacheth another, teacheth thou not thy ſelf; thou that teacheth another he ſhould not ſteal,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.22.</note> why doſt thou ſteal?</p>
            <p>Art not thou a thief, whoſoever thou art, that ſpeaks forth the ſaints words, and do not live their life? When they ſpake forth thoſe words, they ſpake forth their life. Now ſee all of you, who are the Thieves and Robbers that do not come in by the door, which is Chriſt, but clime up another way; thoſe that ſpeak from the Scriptures,<note place="margin">Jer. 2.8.</note> and not from the life that gave forth the Scriptures, they are the thieves that ſteal the word from their Neighbors; theſe are they that ſay,<note place="margin">Jer. 23.30.</note> 
               <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> when he never ſpake to them; theſe are they that handle the Law, and know not the Lord, therefore they ſhall not profit the people.</p>
            <p>Now conſider, be not deceived; though they ſpeak the true words of the Prophets, Chriſt, and the Apoſtles, that doth not make them Miniſters of Chriſt; no, for the Devil ſpake truth when he ſaid, <hi>Chriſt was the Son of God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark 3.11</note> yea, though he ſpoke the truth, the Lord did rebuke him and bid him hold his peace, for he knew he ſpake by his own ſpirit: So conſider, both Prieſt and People, what Spirit you ſpeak from, and meddle not with the Saints words without their ſpirit, leſt the Lord rebuke you for it, but come to the life that gave forth the Scriptures, and then every one will witneſs your profeſſion in them, and the Spirit will lead you into the truth of them, and then will you ſpeak from the word of the Lord made manifeſt in you, and then will you come to live their life that gave forth the Scriptures, which moſt that profeſs the Scriptures are ſtangers to, having got the form of them, but the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is denied by them; therefore they to every good work are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115359:6"/>knowing not the Lord, but living in all maner of fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs, and yet profeſs Scripture to be their rule, and that doth condemn them.</p>
            <p>For ſhame, give over ſuch a profeſſion, for thoſe that profeſs Scripture, and not live the life of it, thoſe do deny it, let them pretend what they will; thoſe that live in pride, in covetouſneſs, in railing, in ſcorning, in fooliſh jeaſting, in wantonneſs, in the luſts of the fleſh, theſe deny the Scripture, for againſt theſe things doth it witneſs.</p>
            <p>Now conſider, you that make a trade with the Saints words, and not live the life; what is the cauſe of your unfaithfulneſs, and the unfaithfulneſs of your hearers? you do not ſtand in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of the Lord, and therefore not profit the people, nor turn the wicked from the evil of their ways and wickedneſs of their doings, but the hand of the Lord is againſt you. Repent, return to your firſt Husband that you may be fruitful: you do pretend that you are the Miniſters of Chriſt, but where is the proof of your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery? are not proud ones proud ſtill, yea more then ever, are not covetous ones ſo ſtill, are not railers, railers ſtill? are not profain ones ſo ſtill, are not drunkards ſo ſtill, are not ſwearers ſo ſtill, are not formiliſts ſo ſtill? what amendment amongſt you this year more then many years before, yet never more ſpeaking then now: the word is the ſame as ever, the power the ſame as ever,<note place="margin">Mich. 3.6, 7, 11.</note> the Lord hath as many to bring home to himſelf as ever, and the power doth as much appear as ever, but not amongſt you: the Lord hath hid his face from you, as is confeſſed by many of you; the wiſe will lay theſe things to heart, but ſcorners will go on in ſcorning: Fear the Lord God of power, and return from your wickedneſs, and he will receive you, and have mercy upon you; but if you go on in theſe ways of wickedneſs, the Lord will forſake you and caſt dung upon you: you have a long while pretended that what you did was by the example of Chriſt, the Prophets and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, theſe you ſay have been your rule, but are you not ſound to be thoſe that are out of the example of Chriſt, of the Prophets and the Apoſtles?</p>
            <p>Ye call Chriſt Lord and Maſter, and ſo he is, <hi>If I then your Lord and Maſter have waſhed your feet, ye alſo ought to waſh one anothers feet, for I have given you an example, that ye ſhould do as I have done to you:</hi> Chriſt was meek and loving, and did in all things obey the will of his Father that ſent him: do you follow this example? Chriſt ſpake nothing of himſelf, but from his Father that ſent him; for, ſaith Chriſt, <hi>I have not spoken of my ſelf, but the Father that ſent me he gave me a commandment what I ſhould ſay and what I ſhould speak:</hi> Do you follow this example? do not you ſpeak your own words, and not from the Father? do you not ſpeak the true words of Chriſt, the Prophets and Apoſtles, but not by the ſpirit
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115359:7"/>of the Father? Is this to follow Chriſts example, the Prophets and Apoſtles example? they ſpake as they were moved by the holy Ghoſt, do you follow their example? but you ſpeak even when you will, and pray when you will, begin when you will, and end when you will; was this their example? you ſhall finde the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, they did not ſo read the propheſie of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> and you ſhall there finde that he did not ſpeak many words; but the word of the Lord came to him again, and ſo he ſpake as he was moved, when the Lord did not ſpeak to him, then he was ſilent: Is this your example? but you can pray by the hour, and ſpeak by the hour, what you have patched up together from their true words; but the Lord doth not ſpeak thoſe words to you; if he had, you would follow their example, and live the life of them. Thoſe the Lord doth ſpeak to, they are not thus limited, neither do they thus limit, but as the Lord doth give them utterance they ſpeak, ſometimes many hours, ſometimes not many words; is this your practices? no, you would think this a ſhame to you. Silence fleſh, that it may not ſpeak before the Lord, but the ſpirit that doth lead into the truth may have the preheminence, that the Lord alone may ſpeak in his own temple; if you did thus ſpeak the true De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of Chriſt, and Prophets and Apoſtles, which is the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, which nothing is to be added to them,<note place="margin">Rev. 22.18, 19.</note> then you would witneſs the word to be a fire, and a hammer; wheat, and not chaff, purifying and cleanſing, the word ingrafting, the immortal ſeed of it, and ſo witneſs light: ſo now conſider, it is not they that know the will of the Father, but thoſe that do it, that ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the bleſſing; no, many ſhall come in that day, and ſay, <hi>Lord, we have propheſied in thy name, and done many miraculous works,</hi> yet the Lord ſhall ſay, <hi>I know ye not, ye are workers of iniquity, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from me;</hi> they had the Scriptures, but not the light of them, therefore friends, be not deceived with fair ſhows, but try all things, try your ſelves, and try your teachers, whether they or you follow Chriſts example; but are not they found out of Chriſts example, the Prophets and Apoſtles example, which were the true meſſengers of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Acts 3.7. and 4.5.</note> that did receive their power from him, and yet were queſtioned by Prieſts, the Profeſſors, by what au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority they did theſe things, and who gave them that authority; ſo it was, though <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> did do a miracle amongſt them, upon one that was lame from the womb of his mother, yet they did queſtion his power; and it came to paſs, that on the morrow that their Rulers, and Elders, and Scribes, and <hi>Annas</hi> the high Prieſt, and <hi>Caiphas,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> and as many as were of the kindred of the Prieſts, were gathered together at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and when they had ſet them in the midſt, they asked them by what Power, or by what Name have ye done this: So it is now this day by the chief Prieſts and their kindred, they ſay by what
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115359:7"/>authority, and who gave them their power, though their power be made manifeſt in bringing home, many a ſoul to the Lord, yet none ſo much as by them oppoſed: the ſame ſpirit that was in them, though they are dead many years agon, yet that ſpirit doth ſtill live, and bring forth the ſame fruits of perſecution;<note place="margin">Acts 5.34.38. Mic. 3.11. Mat. 10.8.</note> therefore take warning how you do oppoſe the work of the Lord, remember <hi>Gamaliels</hi> counſel, leſt you be found fighters againſt him, for we cannot but ſpeak the things that we have heard and ſeen whether it be right in the ſight of God, to hearken unto you more then unto God, judge ye: when Chriſt ſent forth his Prophets and Apoſtles to preach or to publiſh the Goſpel, did he ſend them forth to preach for hire; no, againſt all hirelings they did wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, freely they had received it, and freely they did adminiſter it; they had not a living provided for them of the world, or elſe they would not preach to them; if they had not a ſetled mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in one place, they did remove to another, they did not co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with the world, and ſay, What will you give me; no, this was not their example, but this was their practice: wo were they, if they did not preach the Goſpel, through neceſſity, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, and afflictions were laid upon them; did the Apoſtles of Chriſt receive any thing of the world for to maintain them, was it not the command of Chriſt that they ſhould not ſtay in any houſe to eat or drink, if the people were not worthy; but if they were worthy, there they were to ſtay, and to eat ſuch things as were ſet before them: Is this your example? Did the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> when he was planting the Church of Corinth, receive any thing from them to be a ſupply to him; no, he was chargeable to no man; for that which was lacking, the Brethren which did come from <hi>Macedony,</hi> ſupplied, and in all things, I kept my ſelfe from being burdenſome to you, and ſo will I keep my ſelfe, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.9. is this your example, did not he plant a Vineyard before he did eat the fruit, did not he miniſter ſpiritual things, bringing them to the faith of Chriſt, before he did receive their carnal: is this your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, no yours is contrary: do not you receive temporall of them that never received ſpiritual from you? was this their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample? do you plant a Vineyard before you do eat the fruit of it? no, they are not your example, as is manifeſt by your practiſes: are you not them that walk out of the life of the Apoſtles, and by their life is to be condemned with thoſe, that in the Apoſtles dayes did walk as you do, loving gifts, and preaching for h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re: let your pretence be what it will, if you are found in theſe practices receiving maintenance from the world, or forcing it from them, then you are ſuch which the Prophets and Apoſtles were ſent to cry woe againſt, did ever the Apoſtles take the tenth of mens labours? did ever the Apoſtles take Tithe-Calves, Tithe-Pigs, or Tithe-Eggs, Tithe for Gardens, Tithe-Hay, Tithe-Wood, and ſuch like things; be it known
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115359:8"/>to thoſe that do receive them, and to thoſe that do give them than to me.</p>
            <p>Was this their example, or were ever Tithes paid after Chriſts Aſcenſion, by any, either by the world, or by the Saints for preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt: did <hi>Abraham</hi> ever pay Tithes, but once to <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> and thoſe not of mens labours, but of the ſpoil when he did return home from the Battle. The light hath made you manifeſt, that you do not follow their example, and yet you cry your ſelves up to be the Miniſters of Chriſt. Deal honeſtly with your own ſouls, how dare you ſay, you follow their example, when they did practiſe no ſuch things, but againſt ſuch did teſtifie? how dare you ſay that you are their ſucceſſors, and yet walk in the ſteps of the falſe Apoſtles: for ſhame ſtop your mouthes; own your ſelves where you are, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny this diſhoneſt gain of yours.</p>
            <p>Did ever the Apoſtles ſue any at Law for a maintenance from them? was this their example? doth not Chriſt and the Apoſtles forbid to go to Law, but rather to ſuffer? hath this been your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample? nay, hath not there been many impriſoned by you, pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing double dammages, to the undoing of them, and their Families: lying in priſon, ſome at this day for this very thing: where had you this example,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.40. 1 Cor. 6.7.</note> if this were either Chriſts, the Prophets, or the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles example, prove it if you can by Scripture: if it were not, how ſay you, you are their ſucceſſors, do you not rather reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Popes Clergy,<note place="margin">Read and compare theſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</note> who hath Tithes for their maintenance, and a forced living. But you will ſay, the Civil power doth give you them, therefore you may receive them; but I would know of you, whether it be better for to obey God or Man.</p>
            <p>Do not you know, that you ſhould not receive them, if you will follow the example of Chriſt, and the Apoſtles? hath not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny left them, as knowing them not to be according to the Goſpel-Order, but for the Prieſtly Order;<note place="margin">Numb. 18.21.</note> but it is your gain that will not let you follow their example: thoſe that were the Miniſters of Chriſt, and the Meſſengers of Chriſt, they did cry out againſt all oppreſſion; but you ſtrengthen the hand of the wicked, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Judgement and Juſtice, and makes it ſerve for your own luſts; or you do know that the tenths that are given you by the civil Law, are not the Miniſters of Chriſts portion, neither ever had they any ſuch example; but this is that that doth uphold the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Miniſtry,<note place="margin">Heb. 7.5.11.12, 13, 14.</note> which hath made all Nations drunk with the wine of their fornication.</p>
            <p>Is not this the reaſon why ſo many are put by man into the work of the Miniſtry, becauſe of their ſetled maintenance? would there be ſo many ſent to the Schools of Learning, by their Parents? if it were not for hopes of preferment? Were there nothing of ſelf-ends, neither in Parents or Children,<note place="margin">Heb. 1.2.</note> the Schools would be many times empty: but when they have ſpent their young time in idleneſs,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115359:8"/>without a lawful Calling,<note place="margin">Read and compare one with the other.</note> and ſerved a prentiſhip in the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, then are they fitted, as they ſay, to come and preach to the people, although they have never learned their own Miniſtry: here is the bold preſumption of man; for they chuſe men, and fit them, and ſend them forth into the work of the Miniſtry, they ſend forth labourers into the Lords Harveſt, when it is the work of the Lord ſo for to do; for this was one end of Chriſts leading cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity captive, to give gifts unto men, and he did aſcend on high far above all Heavens, that he might fill all things, and he gave ſome Apoſtles, and ſome Prophets, and ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Paſtors and Teachers, for the perfecting the Saints,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.8.13.</note> for the work of the Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>Do you think Chriſt is not ſufficient to furniſh his Meſſengers as formerly he hath done; but you proud fleſh muſt teach him a way, and ſo be his Counſeller? will not you let him chuſe his own labourers, to work in his own Vineyard, and fit them as himſelfe pleaſeth, is not he with his Church to the end of the World? hath he not ſaid, he will never leave them, nor forſake them:<note place="margin">Gal. 1.1.</note> is not he their King, Prieſt and Prophet, and hath he not ſaid, he will ſend them Paſtors according to his own heart, that ſhall feed his people with knowledge: and now Chriſt promiſes is fulfilling;<note place="margin">Gal. 1.11, 12.</note> but he is not believed by you, but you will chuſe, and you will ſend forth, and you give them their Commiſſion and Approbation, and none is accounted fit, but ſuch as are approved by you. Is this Chriſts example, is not this to take that power to your ſelves, that the Lord did never give you:<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.5.6.</note> is not this to ſet your ſelves above Chriſt, and ſo are indeed the Antichriſts: come down proud fleſh, the Lord will eſtabliſh his Mountain upon the top of all your Mountains, and it ſhall be exalted above the hills, and the people ſhall flowe unto it, and many Nations ſhall come and ſay, Come let us go up to the Mountain of the Lord, and to the houſe of the God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and he will teach us of his wayes, and we will walk in his pathes; for the Law ſhall go forth of <hi>Sion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.12.</note> and the word of the Lord from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> take warning, the Lord will not long take at your hands, for you to chuſe his labourers, to work in his Vineyard; for the day of the Lord of Hoſts ſhall be upon every one that is proud and lofty, and upon every one that is lifted up, and he ſhall be brought low: this day of the Lord is now made manifeſt, though you ſee it not, wherein the lofty looks of man ſhall be humbled, and the haughtineſs of men ſhall be bore down, and the Lord <hi>Alone</hi> ſhall be exalted in that day,<note place="margin">Luke 10.2.3.</note> who art thou proud man that thou ſhouldſt ſtrive with the Lord. Look back to the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of Prieſts formerly, that were approved by man, and ſent forth by man, by the ſame power that you were ſent forth by, and approved by, that is the Biſhops, and read what they were.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Were not they a ſhame and reproach to the Goſpel, living in all
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115359:9"/>manner of filthineſs, and in the abhominations of the Heathen? But you ſay, you were not choſen by them as Biſhops, but as Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters. And were not thoſe the like? might not thoſe that were choſen by them have ſaid the ſame as you do? but is your Presbytery now, or was it then as it was in the Apoſtles dayes?<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14</note> you have got the form of the thing; but where is the life and power, either of your choyce of Miniſters, or other Officers?</p>
            <p>Do you give the gift with the laying on of the hands of the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, as thoſe did: if you had, there would not have been ſo many caſt out for their filthineſs, as there was; but then Miniſters, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Officers were choſe by the Holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 13.2, 3, 4.</note> and then offenders were caſt out by the ſpirit of the Lord, and then Miniſters were ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated to that work by the Spirit not by man, nor by the will of man but by God, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12. I thank Chriſt Jeſus our Lord who hath enabled me for that he counted me faithful,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4.</note> puting me into the Miniſtery. See from whence you are faln and repent, and turn to the Lord, and yet you are exalted, and you are thoſe that the world wonders after, crying you up for the onely Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt, choſe by man, and approved by man, but out of the example of Chriſt, as hath been proved before. Do you not make the Univerſities the two fountains and ſprings, for to ſend forth godly and able Miniſters and Magiſtrates, that out of them may proceed plants to plant the Church and State withall. Is not this your prayer many times? do you not here limit the holy one of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and confine him to your wills? but ſuch as the fountain is, ſuch are the ſtreams; and if ever any come to be called by Chriſt to the work of the Miniſtery which hath been at thoſe fountaines, they do deny the ſtreams of human inventions, as many in this land do and hath done, knowing they were never made for no ſuch uſe nor end, but ſtand directly: againſt Chriſt and the commands of Chriſt. Beware, ſaith the Apoſtle, leſt any man ſpoile you through Philoſophy and vain deceit,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 2.8.</note> after the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of men, after the rudiments of the world, and not after Chriſt, for in him dwelleth all the Godhead bodily, and ye are compleat in him, which is the head of all principality and power. Here is the Saints fulneſs in Chriſt, and their compleatneſs in Chriſt, Chriſt being made to them of God wiſdom, righteouſneſs, ſanctification, and redemption, and ſo need no other wiſdom to be taught by,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30.</note> nor doth it teach by any other, but all his people are taught by him, and ſo they are eſtabliſhed in ſure peace, not car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried about with the cunning ſhiftes of men, whereby they may lye in wait to deceive, but ſpeaking the truth in the love it, they grow up into him in all things, which is the head even Chriſt, and ſo the Church comes to know the manifold wiſdom of God, which is hid from the Learned of the world, but revealed to babes. Come lay all your Crowns down at the feet of Jeſus, and let him that thinkes himſelf wiſe, become a fool that he may be made wiſe: for
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115359:9"/>worldly wiſdom is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nity againſt God, for the world by wiſdom doth not know God, from that eye it is hid, never to be revealed, and exalt not thy ſelf above thy fellow members; but know the ſame light that doth enlighten the eye, the ſame light doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten the whole body, fitly joyned together,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12, 20, 25.</note> and compacted by that which every joynt ſupplieth, according to the effectual wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the meaſure of every part, maketh increaſe of the body unto the edifying of it ſelf in love, and ſo here is no ſchiſme in the body. Here is not one member ſeeks preheminence above a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, but he that would be greateſt, let him be ſervant to the body: Is this your practice? no it is to the contrary, do not you Lord it over Gods heritage, as if you and onely you did know the mind of the Lord,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph</hi> 4.15, 16.</note> and if any man doth not take that for truth which you do deliver or ſhall object againſt it, ſuch a one is a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous fellow, he is running into ſects and Ichiſme, and hypocriſie: but you make a trade of your preaching; and ſhould it be queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned how you came into the Miniſtery, your gain would be loſs which you do receive of the world for your preaching; but know the Lord is come to pluck the skin of the lambe off the back of the wolfe, that he may appear to be ſo,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 2.19:</note> that men may be no longer deceived by you that profeſs you ſollow the example of Chriſt, but upon trial are found to be one with the world, entered into the world, and the world into you, and ſo are at peace one with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but the Lord God of power is breaking your peace, that Chriſt alone may reign in his Temple.</p>
            <p>Therefore beware you Prieſts of the world, how you uphold that which the Lord will deſtroy, leaſt you be found fighters againſt God: but the Prieſts ever laboured to have the power of the world on their ſides.</p>
            <p>O the running, and riding, the plotting, and contriving by the Prieſts to chuſe a perſon that will ſide with them and their intereſt; what meetings and prayings, what ſtirring up of the people to joyn with them all along, with petitioning, and fighting, witneſs many both in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> to drive on their intereſt; theſe things are manifeſt, and yet would be counted the Miniſters of Chriſt: was this their example? are not all the wayes of the Lord hid from you? are your deſires fulfilled? you have asked and received not, becauſe you ask amiſs; ye kill and deſire to have and cannot obtain, that you might conſume it upon your luſts.</p>
            <p>I have heard many of you ſay, the Lord was in the cloud that you could not ſee him; his wayes were very dark to you, yea they were and ſo they are ſtill: in the land of Egypt there is darkneſs, but in the land of Goſhen there is light. Did ever Chriſt or the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles petition for aid for the Goſpel;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.2, 3, 4.</note> but this is your trade, and by this comes in your gain that makes you ſo beſtir you, you do not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115359:10"/>remember that Chriſt will be with his to the end of the world, and will never leave his ſheep without a ſhepherd,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos.</hi> 3.7, 8.</note> but the Lord will have his Goſpel preached to the end of the world, though no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but perſecution, priſoning, killing, or what ever! Did ever the Goſpel flouriſh more then by perſecution;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 8.11, 12.</note> and were not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the faithful witneſſes of the Lord perſecuted by the world and worldly profeſſors?</p>
            <p>Thus it is now, and hath been in all ages? were not the true prophets counted the troublers of <hi>Iſrael?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 24.5.</note> Were not the Apoſtles counted the peſtilent fellows, and ringleaders of Sects, and not fit for to live? Were not the mouthes of the world open againſt them with all manner of revilings, ſcoffings, and ſcornings? Were not profeſſors gainſaying and blaſpheming? Were not ſome hewn aſunder, and ſome ſawne aſunder, whom the world was not worthy;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 13.45</note> in priſons oft, in perils oft, in travels oft, had no certain dwelling place, but ſent about from place to place, from City to City (yet were no vagabonds) in hunger and nackedneſs, hid in caves and dens of the earth, they were halled out of their Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, they were had before Rulers for the witneſſing of Jeſus. Now know, thoſe that the Lord hath ſent forth now to declare the ſame everlaſting Goſpel, their lives are not dear to them. Nay, wo are they if they preach it not, what affliction or perſecution ſo ever from the world they do indure, counting it their joy to ſuffer for Chriſt, who hath called them forth to the work of the Miniſtery. And now is this Scripture fulfilled and fulfilling, that God hath revealed his counſel to babes and ſucklings, and hath hid theſe things from the wife and prudent;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.27, 28<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> for ſo it hath pleaſed him, and God hath choſen the fooliſh things of the world, to confound the wiſe, and God hath choſen the weak things of the world, to confound the things that are mighty, and baſe things of the world, and things that are deſpiſed hath God choſen; yea the things that are not, to bring to nought things that are, that no fleſh ſhould glory in his ſight; but as it is written, Let him that glories glory in the Lord. Praiſed be the Lord for ever; that after this long night of darkneſs, he hath ſent forth his meſſengers to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect us to the true light, that doth lead into purity and holineſs, bringing down all things that would exalt it ſelf:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.26.</note> this is witneſſed in thoſe that do obey it to their everlaſting joy and comfort, unto whom the reproaches of the world is great riches, this I do wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that they do approve themſelves to the conſcience in the ſight of God, and approve themſelves as the Miniſters of God in much patience, in afflictions, in neceſſities, in diſtreſſes, in ſtripes and impriſonments, in tumults, in labors, in watchings and faſtings by pureneſs,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2.</note> by knowledge, by long ſuffering, by kindneſs, by the Holy Ghoſt, by love unfained, by the word of truth, by the peace of God, by the Armor of righteouſneſs, on the right hand, and on
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115359:10"/>the left, by honor and diſhonor, by good report and evil report, as deceivers and yet true, as unknown, and yet well known, as dying and behold we live, as chaſtiſed and not killed as ſorrowful, yet alwayes rejoycing, as poor yet making many rich, as having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing and yet poſſeſſing all things. All that are joyned by one ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to them, in their meaſure this doth witneſs againſt all raven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous beaſts, and the Vultur's eye.</p>
            <p>Now conſider, all ſorts of men, profeſſors and prophane, that do joyn together, for to ſcoff and ſcorn, revile, and perſecute theſe innocent Lambes of Chriſt, which he hath ſent forth among the Wolves of the world, who are rent and torn by you, ſay you had warning; for know whatſoever you do to one his little ones that believes in him, ye do it to himſelf; and ſo it will be taken, and you judged accordingly; and it were better that you had never been born, for the Lord will execute judgement upon all, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince all that are ungodly among you of all your ungodly deeds,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jud.</hi> 14.</note> which they have ungodly committed; and of all your hard ſpeeches which ungodly ſinners have ſpoken againſt them. What you ſpeak againſt the ſervants of Chriſt, you ſpeak againſt Chriſt, all your hard ſpeeches, all your evil ſurmiſings againſt them, is all known to the Lord, who is juſt and righteous, and will not ſuffer the wicked to go unpuniſhed.</p>
            <p>Repent, repent, and turn to the Lord, the great day of the Lord is neer, it is neer, it haſteth greatly, even the great day of the Lord; the mighty man ſhall cry out bitterly, that day is a day of wrath, a day of trouble and diſtreſs, a day of waſtneſs and deſolation, a day of darkneſs and gloomineſs, a day of clouds and thick darkneſs; and I will bring diſtreſs upon men, and they ſhall walk like blinde men, becauſe they have ſinned againſt the Lord, this ſhall they have for their pride, becauſe they reproached and magnified them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt the people of the Lord of hoſtes, the Lord will be terrible unto you, then you will wiſh the mountains to fall upon you and hide you from the preſence of the Lord; ſo terrible will the Lord be to all the enemies of Sion, for he will ſet his Son upon that holy hill, and he will roar out of Sion, and utter his voice out of Jeruſalem and terribly ſhake the earth, and he will famiſh the gods of the earth, and men ſhall worſhip him every one from his place even all the Iſſes of the heathen; for then will I turn to the people a pure language, that they may call upon the name of the Lord, and ſerve him with one conſent;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 3.16</note> and will ſhake all Nations, and the deſire of all Nations ſhall come.</p>
            <p>No wart theſe promiſes fulfilled and fulfilling, praiſes be to the Lord for ever, he hath turned to his people a pure language, and they do ſerve him with one conſent;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and now is the ſhaking all Nations ſhaking earth, and ſhaking heaven, that thoſe things that cannot be ſhaken may remain: therefore take heed you
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115359:11"/>powers of the earth, how you ſet your power againſt this great power of the Lord, leaſt he ſhake you out with the workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, when he ſhall come to cleanſe the Land of evil doers, for at laſt he will make his Jeruſalem a praiſe upon the earth, and he will ariſe and have mercy upon his <hi>Sion.</hi> Behold at that time I will undo all that afflict thee, and will get them praiſe and fame in every land where they have been put to ſhame.</p>
            <p>Conſider this, ye perſecuters, ye ſcoffers and ſcorners, ye ſons of <hi>Iſhmael</hi> who ſcoffes the righteous, and makes a ſcorn of the upright, but the Lord that ſits in heaven ſhall laugh &amp; have you in deriſion, and will mock when your fear cometh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.26, 27.</note> your deſtruction ſhall come like a whirle winde; affliction and anguiſh ſhall come upon you, then ſhall you call, but he will not anſwer you, but ſhall caſt you forth with the workers of iniquity.</p>
            <p>Repent behold the day cometh that ſhall burn as an even, and all the proud, yea all that do wickedly ſhall be ſtuble, and the day that cometh ſhall burn them up, it ſhall leave you neither root nor branch, and ye ſhall be troden under the ſoles of their feet in the day that I ſhall do this, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts.</p>
            <p>Repent all ſcoffers and ſcorners, repent all proud ones which know not what to eat nor what to drink, nor what for to put on, but feeding your ſelves without the fear of the Lord, living like fed beaſts that are fatted againſt the day of ſlaughter, ſetting your ſelves forth with every new and ſtrange faſhion to make you ſeem glorious in the eyes of the world, but the Lord will viſit you for it; ye the day is near at hand, when you ſhall be called to an account for ſpending the Lords goods upon your luſts, every ſtew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard muſt give an account how he hath diſpoſed of his Maſters goods whether for the uſe and ſervice of the Lord, or to ſave your ſelves.</p>
            <p>Repent all luſtful ones above your fellow creatures, as if you had not all one father from whence you did proceed; did not the Lord, of one blood make all Nations that live upon the face of the earth?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17.26</note> remember from whence you came, and whether you are going: as dyes the rich ſo dies the poor, as dyes the wiſe, ſo dyes the fool; there is an end to all fleſh, as fleſh. What advantage is it for you to act in all manner of filthineſs, for a time to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon, and after death to be tormented for ever?</p>
            <p>You act your parts upon the ſtage of this world, and make your folly manifeſt, and then ly down in ſorrow. O the filthy pride that is among the rich and great of the world, the high minded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and diſdainful carriages of moſt of the great ones, brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beating their inferiors, as they call them; be not high minded, nor truſt not in uncertain riches, but in the living Lord, who is an enemy againſt all thoſe that do commit ſuch things, but turn to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115359:11"/>the light that doth diſcover theſe things to be fruits of darkneſs, whoſe end is deſtruction and ſhame for ever; this was and is the main end of the Miniſters of Chriſt and Miniſtery of Chriſt, to tum people from darkneſs to the light, for that which doth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover darkneſs is light, the light maketh all things manifeſt; Chriſt is the light of the world, and the life of Chriſt is the light of the world, and this is the true light that doth inlighten every one that cometh into the world; this light ſhineth in darkneſs, but the darkneſs cannot comprehend it; and therefore will not own it; the world was made by him, and the world knows him not; and this is the condemnation that light is come into the world, and men love darkneſs rather then light, becauſe their deeds are evil, for every one that doth evil hateth the light, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cometh to the light, leaſt his deeds ſhould be reproved, but he that doth truth, cometh to the light, that his deeds may be made manifeſt that they are wrought in God, and he that walketh in this light; there is no occaſion of ſtumbling in him. This light is pure as Chriſt is pure, it is not of man nor nothing of man, but it is in man, it is the gift of God, it is not of mans will but croſſes the will of man, for the will of man is to run away from the Lord, but this would lead the will of man up to the Lord; ſo it is neither him that willeth nor him that runneth, but the Lord that ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth mercy; but the will of man running from the light into dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, runneth away from his own mercy, and ſo his deſtruction is of himſelf; that which doth convince the world of ſin, is that which is not of the world, but would lead men out of the world up to God, from whence it came. This light is the gift and talent of God which he hath inveſted every man withall, it is not mans own, but every man muſt be countable how he doth imploy it, this is the grace of God that hath appeared to all men, and it teacheth the Saints to deny all ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, and to live righteouſly, ſoberly, and godly in this preſent evil world: but this by the world's turned into wantonneſs, and done deſpite unto: ſuch by the light may come to know the way of righteouſneſs, which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural light cannot diſcover, for if they after they have eſcaped from the filthineſs of the world, through the knowledge of the Lord and of the Saviour Jeſus Chriſt are yet again tangled therein and over run, the latter end is worſe then their beginning, for it had been better for them not to have known the way of righteouſneſs, then after they have known it to turn from the holy command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment given unto them, but it is come unto them according to the true Proverb, <hi>The dogg is returned to his vomit, and the ſow that was waſhed, to the wallowing in the mire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here is the worlds condemnation: did not this light reprove the world of ſin, the world would have no condemnation, but now the world hath no cloak for their ſin. Man will not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115359:12"/>becauſe he hath not a talent to improve, but becauſe they, have a talent, and doth not improve it, but hide it in the earth, and are ſloathful ſervants, ſo at the laſt day every mouth will be ſtopped, and all the world be found guilty before the Lord, and it will be juſt with the Lord to take away his talent, and caſt him into outer darkneſs; therefore while you have the light, walk in the light, that you may be the children of the light. How oft hath Chriſt by his light diſcovered to you your deeds of darkneſs, and if ever they were diſcovered to you, which I know they have, it was by this light. How oft hath it checked you, in ſecret when no eye did ſee you, telling you that you ſhould not ſwear nor lie, nor be drunk, nor take Gods name in vain, nor do any evil, but to do to all men as you would they ſhould do to you. This is the love of God to every one that would lead men up to the Lord out of ſin, out of pollution: and minding it, it would lead to the father of light, that ye ſhould return no more to folly, but if you ſleight it, it will not alwayes ſtrive with you: for it is impoſſible for thoſe that were once enlightned, and have taſted of the heavenly gift, and were made partakers of the Holy Ghoſt, and have taſted of the good word of God and the powers of the world to come, if they ſhall fall away to renew them again by repentance, ſeeing they crucifie to themſelves the Son of God afreſh, and put him to an open ſhame.</p>
            <p>If thoſe that did deſpiſe <hi>Moſes</hi> Law died without mercy under two or three witneſſes, of how much ſoarer puniſhment ſuppoſe ye, ſhall he be thought worthy, who hath troden under feet the Son of God, and hath done deſpite to the ſpirit of grace?</p>
            <p>Conſider theſe things, you ranting ſpirits that hath turned the grace of God that ſhould lead you to repentance, into wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and make it your cloak for your wicked practices, running in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſin with greedineſs, but you ſhall not proceed, for your folly is made manifeſt to all men, you are a ſtink to the Lord, and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to man; wo be to you that draw iniquity with cords of vanity, and ſin with cart ropes.</p>
            <p>Wo be to you that ſpeak good of evil, and evil of good, which our darkneſs for light, and light for darkneſs, that put bitter for ſweet, and ſweet for ſowre; therefore as the fire devoureth the ſtuble, and as the chaffe is conſumed of the flame, ſo your root ſhall be rottenneſs, and your bud ſhall riſe up like duſt, becauſe ye have caſt away the law of the Lord of hoſts, and contemned the word of the holy one of Iſrael: this is the will of God your ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, that every one of you ſhould know how to poſſeſs his veſſel in holineſs and honor, and not in the luſts of concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence, even as the Gentiles which know not God; for God hath not called any unto uncleaneſs, but out of uncleanneſs unto ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, for thoſe that are Chriſts have crucified the world with the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115359:12"/>affections &amp; luſts, every one in their meaſures growing into confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to the head Chriſt Jeſus: the wrath of the Lord will feaze up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, except you return from your evil to the Lord, from whence you are faln; the world ſhall ſee it, and fear before the Lord, the Lord will not hide it, it ſhall be made manifeſt to man. If your conſciences be not ſeared as with a hot iron, or if you are not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven up to a reprobate minde paſt feeling, if you have not ſolde your ſelves to work wickedneſs; there is that in your conſcience that doth convince you, that living in filthineſs in the fruites of the fleſh is not to be in conformity to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Hear what is ſaid, O God thy Throne is for ever, the Scepter of thy Kingdom is a Scepter of righteouſneſs; thou haſt loved righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and hated iniquity, wherefore God, even thy God hath annointed thee with the oile of gladneſs above thy fellows; and know, though your good works and holy life will not ſave you, yet God hath ordained good works that men ſhould walk in them, and without holineſs no man ſhall ſee the Lord, but you will finde the Lambe to be a Lion that will render vengeance upon all that obey him not in flames of fire: truely I can ſay with the Apoſtle, having known the terrors of the Lord againſt ſin, I do perſwade you for our God is a conſuming fire; the wicked ſhall not ſtand in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</p>
            <p>I charge you in the name of the Lord to take warning, and to minde that pure light which leads out of theſe works of impurity, leſt you be like thoſe corrupt trees: without fruit twice dead and plucked up by the roots, &amp; ſo be cut aſſunder from all good, for the wrath of God is revealed from heaven againſt all ungodlineſs and unrighteouſneſs of men which withhold the truth in unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; be not high minded but fear; for aſſuredly the Lord will not quit the guilty that will run on in ſin without repentance, and count it part of his perfection, but ſnares fire and brimſtome will he rain upon the head of the ungodly: know you not that the unrighteous ſhall not inherit the kingdom of God? Be not deceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for theſe things cometh the wrath of God upon the children of diſobedience; the Lord will not be mocked, but if you do ſow to the fleſh, of the fleſh you ſhall reap corruption: thoſe that did commit theſe things, had the light; and following the light were led out of darkneſs, and did ſee thoſe fruites of darkneſs, and were aſhamed.</p>
            <p>Now conſider this, both Prieſt and people, that ſay it is a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral light: nature doth not, nor cannot diſcover the ſin that is in nature, for this light doth convince and condemn the ſin in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture many yeers paſt: now that which doth reprove of ſin is not natural but ſpiritual, for it doth convince of ſpiritual wickedneſs and leads into holineſs; it is the light of life to thoſe that do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey it, and condemnation to them that ſin againſt it, yea I wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs it is ſo, this is the true guide, this is the door to come to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115359:13"/>Chriſt and the Father thoſe that do own the light are made the children of the light and of the day, but thoſe that live in ſin are dead while they live; they are enemies to the Lord, and ſo hate the light, and will not bring their deeds to the light, leaſt they ſhould be reproved.</p>
            <p>Now for thoſe that do get the Saints words, ſteal the true words that were given forth from the light, and not walk in the life; thoſe are the thieves and robbers that do not come in by the door, but clime up ſome other way;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.1.10, 12, 13,</note> theſe are they that do make merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize of the letter, and ſo deceive the hearts of the ſimple: thoſe that ſpoke forth thoſe words they ſpake forth their life, they did live them they ſpake what they had heard and ſeen, and not from other men, but did believe therefore they ſpake: and when you come to the faith, then you may ſpeak what is made manifeſt to you, going not before nor beyond your meaſure you have received, but ſtanding in ſilence in the counſel of the Lord,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20, 21.</note> and then you will his power <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that gave forth the Scriptures, and then you will know they are of no private interpretation, but holymen ſpake them forth as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt. This will bring you to the life that was before Scripture was; to the beginning, to know the truth which the Scriptures are a true declaration of, and ſo you will grow up to the life of the Scripture, which the world are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from, though they have the Scriptures, and can talke from the Scriptures, and can preach from the Scriptures, and can migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily plead for the Scriptures, and ſay, what will you deny the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and muſt ye not be ruled by the Scriptures, and mighty zealous to the ſight of the world, for the Scriptures; but to the life are enemies not having the life of the Scriptures, and ſo are condemned by the Scriptures; therefore it is a book ſealed to the wiſdom. The firſt wiſdom cannot comprehend them; they were never given forth by it, that rends them that wreſts them, and ſtretches them to finde out their meanings, but from that eye it is hid, never to be revealed: here, comes in the private interpretation, here comes meanings to the Scripture, one ſaith this is the meaning of this place, another he conceives it means thus, and ſo conceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings &amp; meanings is put upon them; from hence comes all Sects and opinions from dark minds, not from the Scripture, for that was gave forth from the ſpirit of unity and peace: but from the dark minds a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes debates and ſtriſe, vain janglings and contentions, this is from the firſt wiſdon, that would aſpire to know the things of God, but cannot, for it is earthly, ſenſual, and deviliſh, and none come to know the Scriptures but thoſe that have the life that gave forth the Scriptures, and that brings to the life of the Scriptures, and ſo there is no jurring nor wreſting of Scriptures to their own deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which thoſe that are unlearned in that which gave forth the Scriptures do.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:115359:13"/>
Here is the ſubtilty of the Prieſts to keep the people in igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, they tell them the ignorant and unlearned they do wreſt the Scripture to their own deſtruction, but never tell the people, It is ſuch as are not learned by Chriſt by the ſpirit that gave forth the Scriptures; but makes you believe thoſe are the learned that know the Latin, Greek, and Hebrew, which they call the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</p>
            <p>Now conſider all people, whether the wreſting of the Scriptures be by the learned or the unlearned: what preaching, what writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and printings, what wreſtings and wringings are amongſt the learned, ſo called? the one he writes for Free-will and Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal redemption, another he writes and printes againſt it; one writes for infants baptizing, comes another, and he writes againſt him; one writes for a Sabbath, the other writes, preaches, and printes againſt them; nay further, if learning, as they ſay, keep men from wreſting the Scriptures: Why do they finde fault with the Jeſuites for ſo doing, they are as learned as any of you, and do as well know that you call the original: but not many learned, but not many wiſe, but the Lord hath choſen the poor of the world to be rich in faith, and heirs of the kingdom, and God doth reveal his ſecrets to Babes and ſucklings; therefore ſilence deceivers, for <hi>Peter</hi> that gave forth that Epiſtle to the Saints, did not ſay, thoſe that were not Scholars, and ſo unlearned,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10 to the 3, 5.</note> for ſo he was not learned himſelf as the Scriptures doth witneſs. Now who wreſts this Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures you or the unlearned? When <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> were brought before the chief Prieſts, and they did perceive that they were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned men and ignorant, they took knowledge that they had been with Jeſus, <hi>Act.</hi> 4.13. But this will not you do; acknowledge that Jeſus Chriſt doth now ſo teach the unlearned and ignorant, but makes the people believe you are the onely learned, when the wayes of the Lord are hid from you. The way of the Lord is a way of holineſs; the unclean cannot paſs over it, but the waifaring man, though a fool ſhall not erre therein, but the Scriptures are hid from all the outward learning of the world never to be revealed: they are a book that is ſealed with ſeven ſeals, and none can open them, but the Lion of the Tribe of <hi>Juda:</hi> never did humane lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning open one of the ſeals nor never ſhall do, but thoſe that are taught by Chriſt, are led by the ſpirit of Chriſt into the power of them, into the truth of them, into the life of them, and ſo the ſeals come to be opened; for the ſpirit ſearcheth all things, yea the deep things of God, and no man knows<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the things of God, but the ſpirit of God, &amp; he to whom the ſpirit doth reveal them: for the natural man in his higheſt wiſdom is emnity againſt the Lord, for man by wiſdom knows not God. Come down proud fleſh that would aſpire to know the things of God by the ſerpent's wiſdom, from whom it is hide; the firſt wiſdom hath a portion in them, but it is
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115359:14"/>the plagues and wees that are to reſt upon it, it ſhall never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the kingdom, the lake is prepared for it, it can ſpeak of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, but perſecute the power where ever it is manifeſt; the wo of the Lord is upon it, it hath been a murderer from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, it would murder the righteous ſeed wherever it is made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt; it is an enemy to man, it is an enemie to the Lord, it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was ſubject to him: and from this wiſdom do they ſpeak, that do not live the life of the Scriptures, and ſuch are to be ſhut out from the Scriptures, and to own their portion, which are the curſes: they were not made for men that love vain janglings and contentions, they were given forth from a ſpirit of unity; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſilence vain janglers, meddle not with them that are not your portion the Scriptures; they are profitable for doctrine, for reproof and correction, and he that adds his own meanings to them or takes from them, is curſed of the Lord, as they are. They are profitable for thoſe Ends the Lord gave them forth,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15, 16.</note> without ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to them, thoſe that ſpoke them forth were guided by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of truth, and they ſpake forth their own meanings.</p>
            <p>Now conſider what a contradiction and confuſion do both pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and people run into: they do confeſs they were immediately in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired by the Holy Ghoſt when they ſpake forth the Scriptures, and yet they will put meanings and addings to their words; as if there were ſomething wanting in them, that the Apoſtles and Prophets did not ſee when they did write them. Here is the ſubtilty of the firſt wiſdom that would give the Prophets and Apoſtles good words, but would give forth his meanings upon their words, this is the Antichriſt and the deceiver, for to make a trade of them, giving meanings to them. Is not this exalting your ſelves above the wiſdom of God, and running into the invention, and ſo through fained words makes merchandiſe of the people, ſelling the letter for money, which was ſpoke forth freely, and by this ungodly gain, live you and your wifes and children in pride which is manifeſt: but come to the firſt principal that gave forth the Scriptures, and you will ſee the life of them, and witneſs the truth of them, every one in your meaſures, and then there will be no wreſtings to finde out their meanings: by the light you may read them, and your ſelves, and know your portion in them, but not knowing the life of them though you know all the parts of them, and can ſpeak and preach from them, yet you are perſecuters of the life of them. For the Jews did know as much of the letter as any, but when the Life came him they did perſecute: they did know the Latin, Greek, and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, but perſecuted the Original which is Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.28</note> and were ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies againſt him, and yet did know the Scriptures in the form of them, and did ſearch the Scriptures. Be not deceived with vain ſhewes, but come to the life and ſubſtance of truth, as it is in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and the truth will make you free to ſerve the Lord with fear
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115359:14"/>which is the beginning of wiſdom, it keep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> it will ſhew the deceits that doth lodge in the heart, &amp; the light will lead you out of them: it will ſhew you deceit under what pretence ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, it will ſhew you that thoſe that are Miniſters of Chriſt, and Ambaſſadors of Chriſt have not their meſſage to ſeek, and ſo run to be holpen by another, &amp; preach from that which is made ready to their hands, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. Read the ſixteenth, but they have ſalt in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſavor withal at all ſeaſons; they ſhall not need to run to old Authors to patch &amp; piece up Sermons, and to write them down and tell the people this is the word of the Lord, when he never ſpake that unto them; this is their artificial preaching, that their ſtudy and Art have furniſhed them with all; this is their boldneſs before the Lord, to ſpeak their own inventions, and not the word of the Lord.</p>
            <p>The word of the Lord is life and power, the word of the Lord doth ſanctifie, the word of the Lord doth ingraft, the word of the Lord's a ſword to cut down, the word of the Lord is fire, the word of the Lord doth purifie, the word of the Lord is a hammer,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.17</note> but where are theſe things witneſſed amongſt you, where is the power of the word? Whom hath it ſanctified, whom hath it ingrafted?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12.</note> whom hath it cut down? what hath it burned up? is your Lead and Tin conſumed, are you purified by it, what hath it broke down amongſt you, doth not your high thoughts ſtand ſtill? doth not your own wills ſtand ſtill? doth not pride and covetouſneſs ſtand ſtill? doth not wrath ſtand ſtill? doth not envy ſtand ſtill? do not theſe fruites of the fleſh and ſuch like ſtand? Flatter not your ſelves,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.21.</note> for ſuch things cometh the wrath of God upon the children of diſobedience; thoſe that ſpake the word of the Lord, witneſſed theſe things to paſs upon them, and ſo they did; firſt learnt their own Miniſtery thorow the death of the firſt wiſdom,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 23.29.</note> and ſo came to witneſs the Miniſtery of death to be glorious, and ſo came to witneſs <hi>Moſes;</hi> and never none come to witneſs the glorious Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of life, but come to witneſs the glorious miniſtration of death: death doth paſs upon all men, for all men have ſinned, and ſo come to witneſs deaths reign from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Moſes;</hi> who is the figure of him that was to come, and ſo come to witneſs, that as ſin hath raigned unto death, even ſo grace reigns thorow righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs unto eternal life thorow Jeſus Chriſt our Lord: and ſo came to witneſs both ſtates of death and life, and ſo came to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the Prophets, <hi>John,</hi> and the Apoſtles, and witneſs the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of peace and life, this was their way they went in, theſe were the ſootſteps of the flock of Chriſt, and then went forth to preach to the world, and did gather a people out of the world by their Miniſtery, and there were daily added to the Church, ſuch as ſhould be ſaved, and thoſe that were thus gathered by the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal word living in them, were of one heart and one minde, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115359:15"/>they were the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the Lord, and thoſe did edifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother in their moſt holy faith: they were not of the world, but choſen out of the world, and the Church vvas in God and in Chriſt, and it is the pillar and ground of truth, the fulneſs of him that doth fill all things,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.11, to the 15.</note> all members of his body, for both he that ſanctifieth, and they who are ſanctified, are all of one, for which cauſe he is not aſhamed to call them brethren, ſaying, I will declare thy name among my brethren; they are begotten by the immortal ſeed of God, partakers of the Divine nature, the Sons of God, living ſtones builded upon the rock Chriſt Jeſus, in vvhom the whole building fitly framed together, groweth up to a holy Temple in the Lord, and from his Holy Temple doth he make known his will, to the intent that novv unto the principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and powers in heavenly places might be known by the Church the manifold wiſdom of God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.10.</note> Therefore ſilence proud fleſh, that would be exalting it ſelf above your fellow members.</p>
            <p>Now profeſſors ſee and try if it be thus with you and your teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, can they witneſs this way into the Miniſtery? or can you wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that you are of this Church of the firſt born, whoſe names are vvritten in heaven, and come to the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect. If not in your meaſures; flatter not your ſelves with a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, and a Church, and Ordinances for it vvill not avail you. Remember the Jews I ſpake of, before their Ordinances and their Priveleges were very great, they had the true form, but wanted the power, they did offer ſacrifices; they did obſerve Sabbaths and nevv Moons,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.13, 14, 15, 16, 17.</note> and had ſolemne dayes; they had obligations and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe; yet theſe were counted by the Lord iniquity; the ſoul of the Lord hated them, they were a burden to him, he was weary to bear them, and though they made many prayers, yet he would not hear them yet theſe were ordinances of the Lords appointing, there vvas not a ceaſing to do evil, and a learning to do vvell, they did not ſeek judgement nor relieve the oppreſſed, nor judge the fatherleſs, nor defend the vviddovv; there vvas no fruites of righteouſneſs brought forth in their high profeſſion, a fruitleſs profeſſion, reaching at the ſhaddovvs, but did neglect the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: friends deal honeſtly vvith your ſelves, do you think the profeſſion of truth vvill ſerve your turns, and ſtand you in any ſtead before the Lord. When the ſecrets of all hearts ſhall be laid open; they that have the form of the truth and not the povver,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. to the 7.</note> vve are commanded from ſuch to turn avvay; and vvill not the Lord turn avvay from ſuch vvhich he hath commanded us to turn avvay from; yea he vvill: of ſuch ſort are thoſe that lead filly vvomen captive, ever learning, and never able to come to the knovvledge of the truth. Is it not thus in your Aſſemblies vvhich are ſo great, ſome learning ten yeers, ſome tvventy yeers, ſome fourty yeers, ſome threeſcore yeers, and yet ignorant of the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115359:15"/>very firſt principle of that which turns the minde to God, and ſo no good do know, but ever Learning: when for the time yee ought to be teaching; ye had need that one teach you again, the firſt principles of the oracles of God, theſe are the houſe creepers, for had <hi>Paul,</hi> ſpoke againſt preaching in a private houſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 28.29, 20, 31.</note> he had ſpoke againſt his own practice, for it was his manner ſo for to do he did preach in his own hired houſe, and did diſpute in markets and reaſon in the Jews Synagogues with the devout perſons daily, and how oft was <hi>Paul</hi> haled out, beaten and ſtoned, while ſome ſuppoſed he had been dead; ſome ſaid, what will this babler ſay: they counted it new doctrine and ſtrange things; and thus it is at this day, calling it a diſturbance ſo for to do, and by the ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are perſecuted. Now as thoſe were then haled,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 5.25.</note> rent and torn read the Scriptures and ſee if theſe things be not ſo, and there you may finde your own actions done by the ſame ſpirits; therefore boaſt not your ſelves, but this is your Church orders; for ſhame diſown ſuch filthy practices, and ſee what ſpirits you do joyn with: thoſe that are of the world, thoſe are beloved of the world, for the world doth love her own, but thoſe that are not of the world,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17.17, 18.</note> the world doth hate them; there is emnity put between the ſeed of the woman, and the ſeed of the Serpent; never can thoſe be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled, the evil ſpirit knows the evil ſpirit in another, though one hath got the form and words of truth, if the life be wanting, the ſpirit of the prophane world, and their ſpirits will joyn toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to perſecute the power; but as then he that was born after the fleſh, perſecuted him that was born after the ſpirit,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.2.</note> even ſo it is now. It is no new thing when the Church was ſcattered about and went up and down preaching the Goſpel, and had no certain dwelling places, but their habitation was in God: how were they hated by the world, and made the very off-ſcowring of it, of whom the world was not worthy; they were ſtrangers to them; and therefore hated by them, but to entertain ſtrangers forget not;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.10</note> oppreſs not a ſtranger becauſe he is a ſtranger, when the widdows were taken into the Church, they were well reported of for good works; if ſhe hath brought up her children, if ſhe hath lodged ſtrangers; if ſhe hath waſhed the Saints feet. What Church is yours that will not do this to ſtrangers, but perſecute them, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon them, ſpeak all manner of evil of them, when they offer violence to no man.</p>
            <p>Conſider this both Prieſt and people, is it not thus with you? are not theſe fruits made manifeſt, and yet you are not aſhamed to call your ſelves a Church, you are indeed the Synagogues of Satan, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I will make them of the Synagogue of Satan, which ſay they are Jews, and are not but do lie, Behold I will make them to come and worſhip before thy feet, and to know that I have loved thee: he is not a Jew that is one owardly, but he is a Jew that is
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115359:16"/>one inwardly, and Circumciſion is that of the heart in the ſpirit and not in the letter,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.32.</note> whoſe praiſe is of God not of men. Now where the heart is purified, fruites of perſecution doth not appear, nor neither can they; but there love, gentleneſs to all men doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, doing by others as they would be done to. But if theſe fruits do ſtill remain among you, lie not againſt the truth, your Religion is in vain, it will not endure the fire; but this is the National Church that are baptized,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.27.</note> but not into Chriſt, and here is the world made the Church, of whom Chriſt is not the head, nor they his members;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3, 4</note> and here the world reſts, as if they were the people of the Lord, and if any doth come to ſpeak to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, then they are all of an uproare like bruit beaſts. Do not your teachers joyn with the world in feaſtings, in idle ſpeeches, and in fooliſh jeaſtings that do adminiſter no grace to the hearers, telling tales and ſtories which are pleaſing to the fleſh, which they do ſoon receive,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 16.5.</note> for it is one with them, and ſo prophaneneſs is gone forth from the Prieſts: the Miniſters of Chriſt, their life was an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and pattern of holineſs, but you ſtrengthen the hands of the wicked, and diſhonor the Lord of purity and holineſs. Is this to keep your ſelves unſpoted of the world; are not theſe ſpots in your feaſts to feed your ſelves without fear, and joyn with the world; if you did reprove them ſharply when you did hear of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſavory words, not ſeaſoned with grace, they would not endure your company: it would be as fire amongſt them, <hi>But like Prieſt like people;</hi> the Miniſters of Chriſt, they ſay, have no fellowſhip with the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitful works of darkneſs, but rather reprove them that they may be aſhamed: is this your practice? no, it is not: you go from place to place a feaſting into all companies,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.4, and 11.</note> and ſo get the love of all, but wo be to you: you joyn with the world, and the great ones of the world, and have their perſons in admiration becauſe of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, bowing and cringing and worſhipping the ſeed of <hi>Haman,</hi> which <hi>Mordcai</hi> would not do you: are reſpecters of perſons, and ſo are tranſgreſſors of the Law of God; this you to do get a living from them though they are not for Chriſt but for their luſts and pride, moſt of them: theſe are beloved by you, and you do not ſpeak againſt them becauſe of your gain,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jud.</hi> 16.</note> and the honor you have from them; you ſpeak of ſin in the general, and live the life of it, and ſo it is put off from the one to the other;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.9.</note> but which of you do as the prophet did to <hi>David,</hi> ſay, thou art the man: come home to them, and ſpeak in particular, and then you will try them, deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faithfully, not fearing the face of man which muſt periſh, but approve your hearts to the Lord: is this practiſed among you? is not the contrary? do you not daube the great ones with untempered mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heſt.</hi> 3.2.</note> ſpeaking peace to the wicked? Did you forſake and ſhun their companies, and not joyn with them in pride and filthineſs and works of the fleſh, they would ſoon hate you, or their filthy practices
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115359:16"/>practiſes: there would be no living thus, but a ſeparation you would ſee. But are not fruits of pride and covetuouſneſs which is idolatry, fruites of envy and malice, made manifeſt among your Church and hearers; theſe fruits maketh it manifeſt, that you are one with the world, ſay what you will. Are not they the falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets that are entered into the world, in fellowſhip with the world, beloved of the world. Who is it that doth ſide with you, for to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend you, when any doth come from the Lord to ſpeak to you, to leave your deceits? Do not the rude multitude ſide with you, ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, drunkards, ſcoffers and railers, and your profeſſors al together tearing and rending like ravenous beaſts: ſee now where you are, what ſpirit joyns for you; be aſhamed that ever ſuch beaſts ſhould take your parts: did ever ſuch bruites &amp; heathens take part with the Apoſtles when they were halled out of their Synagogues, no they did not, as it was then, ſo it is now. See now where is your Religion, the pure Religion reacheth to do by another as ye would be done by, not to tear and rend like beaſts of prey your fellow creatures,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 19.32, 36, 37, 39, 40.</note> beating and ſmiting of them; are theſe the fruites of the ſpirit? no, they are not, but fruites of the fleſh. Is this your Church or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, be aſhamed for ever, that ſuch ſhould joyn with you: but by your fruites you are known, and the fruites of your Miniſtery received from man is now made manifeſt, the day hath made you manifeſt that theſe are works of darkneſs proceeding from darkneſs, and will end in darkneſs.</p>
            <p>O the deceit of ſome of the chief profeſſors in the Town of <hi>Starfford!</hi> when there come one into their place of meeting to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare againſt the Prieſts deceit: before they did know what was ſpok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, ſhe was haled out by theſe profeſſors, which were then officers, and was led by them to the Cage, and there ſhe did ſit ſeven hours, where ſhe was piſſed on, and ſpit on by thoſe bruites of <hi>Starfford,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.4, 5, 6, 7, 8.</note> theſe profeſſors knowing of it, which they did tell me, did grieve their hearts for to ſee; and about two or three of the clock, did come to my houſe to me to know whether I would receive her, and I did tell them I would, but they went away and did not bring her tell ſix of the clock at night, here was the deceit of you made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, had it grieved your hearts, as you ſaid it did, Why did not you ſooner releaſe her, but the double hearted man God will judge. Know, that mercy to your fellow creature had been better then ſacrifice, but thus is the heart made manifeſt, that it may be known by the fruits of it. The next day ſhe was carried to a Juſtice, thinking to laſe her in priſon, but when they came there, they had none to accuſe her: thus was their folly made manifeſt. She came a ſecond time to their meeting where ſhe was haled out like a dog, and the officers did turn her out of the grave-yard, to the mercies of the heathen, who rent her, and did tear her, pulling
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115359:17"/>her head tire oft, pulling her by the hair of the head, and throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her down in the ſtreet as ſhe paſſed along to come to a friends houſe, which is nigh half the quarter of a mile from the ſteeple houſe, howling and ſhouting at their fellow creature? was it not your office to ſee the peace kept, that theſe bruites might not make a prey of her? had not a ſtranger which was at our meeting took her part, and reſcued her from the violence of thoſe heathen what he could, he did ſee no other but they would have killed her.</p>
            <p>Be aſhamed that ever ſuch wickedneſs ſhould be ſuffered in a town profeſſing Chriſt; you Magiſtrates had warning to deal juſtly to love mercy, to walk humbly with the Lord, not to reſpect the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of men in judgement, but to deal righteouſly according to that righteous Law of God in the conſcience: was this a righteous act of yours to leave your fellow creature to the mercy of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then. Take counſel together, and it ſhall come to nought, ſpeak the word and it ſhall not ſtand, for God is with us. Oh, all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple will walke in the name of his God, and we will walk in the name of the Lord our God for ever and ever, <hi>Micha</hi> 4.6.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:115359:17"/>
            <head>DARKNESSE Denyed by the CHILDREN OF LIGHT.</head>
            <p>IN the fourth moneth, upon the ſixth day of the moneth, I went to <hi>John Pains</hi> houſe of <hi>Starford,</hi> to know of him, if he did not receive a letter of mine that was ſent me from <hi>Cambridge</hi> from <hi>James Blackly</hi> Juſtice of the peace, and he ſaid he had none of it; but <hi>James Blackly</hi> asked the Coachman that did bring it, and he ſaid it was delivered to Mr. <hi>Pain</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Starford,</hi> his name being the ſame with mine, both of us being named <hi>John Pain:</hi> but if he had or hath it, and doth deny it, it is his deceit: this was the cauſe of my going to his houſe. And then when I was there with him, he did begin with me about ſome words that I did ſay to him about the publike Miniſtery, as it doth now ſtand (the National Miniſtery) that I did ſay the ſpirit of the Lord in their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery was departed from them, that they ſhould not convert one ſoul more to the Lord by their Ministery, which thing was true, I did ſo ſay to him and ſo I ſhall do ſtill; and the fruites of it ſhall appear more and more as they ſtand contrary to the commands of Chriſt, they ſhall not, as is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved they do they that neither follow the example of Chriſt, Prophet, nor A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, they ſhall not profit the people; their preaching is like the blood of a dead man, as is manifeſt: they have the form of truth, but the power is denyed by them, and ſo the power is not made manifeſt among them for this many yeers; but this power was by thee denied, for thou did tell me thou hadſt not the infallible ſpirit of <hi>Paul,</hi> if not that ſpirit,<note place="margin">J</note> then another; the ſpirit in the Saints is but one in all, and is the ſpirit
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115359:18"/>of truth that leads into all truth, and ſhews things to come, even the ſpirit of truth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.17.</note> whom the world cannot receive, becauſe it ſeeth him not neither knoweth him, but we know him, for had welleth with us, and ſhall be in us; and this ſpirit is the ſame as ever; this ſpirit was in <hi>Paul,</hi> in the Prophets, in the Saints, that ever were or ever ſhall be. From this ſpirit was the Scripture gave forth, and none but the ſpirit can reveal the Myſteries of God in them, for no man doth know the things of God but the Spirit of God, and he to whom the Spirit of God doth reveal them, and he that hath not the Spirit of Chriſt is note of his; and this ſpirit is the ſpirit of Revelation now in the Saints, and no man knows any thing as he ought to know it but what is revealed by the ſpirit.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11</note>
            </p>
            <p>It is recorded in Scripture that the Spirit beareth witneſs with our ſpirits,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9.</note> that we are the ſons of God. How doth it witneſs, but by revealing to our ſpirits <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it is ſo. This is the earneſt of our inheritance; this is the intrance into the everlaſting kingdom, for there none of our names after the fleſh are ſet down, but this maketh known the white ſtone and the new name which no man doth know but thoſe that do receive it, and this ſpirit of revelation and the Apoſtle pray for, for the Church of the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> that the God and father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the father of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou the ſpirit of wiſdom and revelation in the knowledge of him:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.17, 18. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.4, 5, 6.</note> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ther but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Son, and he to whom the Son doth reveal him; ſo revelations are not ceaſed, as might be proved by many places of the Scripture: yea I witneſs againſt all gain-ſayers that Scripture fulfilled in me, <hi>Joh. 16.13.</hi> That he will ſhew you things to come.</p>
            <p>This I witneſs is truth, and many with me will witneſs the ſame; theſe things are hid from wiſe men, and revealed to babes, the weak things of the world confound the ſtrong and might; glory be to thy name for ever and ever.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13.</note> This ſpirit is in all his Saints, and this ſpirit is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, it cannot lye, it is the ſpirit of truth, and leads into all truth and it abideth with his for ever, and is the ſame as ever was, and is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible. Now, as ever, this thou didſt deny, and didſt ſay, thou hadſt not the infallible ſpirit of <hi>Paul,</hi> the ſpirit I told thee was but one in all the Saints, and if thou hadſt not that infallible ſpirit, thy ſpirit <hi>I</hi> did deny: thou didſt ſtand for to maintain it by Argument, and I gave the Bible to prove it there, but thou didſt not, but thou didſt ſay thou couldſt do it, but it muſt then be by ſome new Scripture of thy own making by that fallible ſpirit of thine: the old Scripture that was given forth by the infallible ſpirit will not do it, but that witneſſeth and I witneſs with it againſt thee, that, this denying thou haſt not the ſpirit that gave forth the Scriptures, and art no Miniſter of Chriſt. And here I charge thee to have a falſe ſpirit,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.1.</note> for thou not having the ſame ſpirit that gave forth the Scripture, then another, and ſo a falſe ſpirit, and a ſpirit of evil, and here thy ſpirit is tryed as the Scripture ſaith, Try the ſpirits and it is found to be a ſeducing eye, leading from the anointing in the Saints
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115359:18"/>which is infallible, and knows no difference between the infallible ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God in man and mans own ſpirit which is fallible, but the anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting which ye hath received of him abideth in you, and ye need not that any man teach you, but as the ſame anointing teacheth you all things, and is truth and is no lye, and even as it hath taught you, ye ſhall abide in him: that ſpirit that doth draw away any from this anointing is the ſpirit of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, and the fallible ſpirit that the falſe Prophets ever had to oppoſe the infallible ſpirit where it was manifeſt: thou dideſt then tell me thou hadſt admoniſhed me twice, and told me the danger that was like to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.2 to 28.</note> for thou didſt ſay I was now grown obſtinate; and then didſt tell me an Heretick after the firſt and ſecond admonition thou waſt to reject, but thou not having the infallible ſpirit that gave forth the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</p>
            <p>Thy caſting me out I do not regard, they are nothing to me they will not enter, they were not words ſpake forth from the life, as may be known by them. One of the times, thou didſt call me Coxcomb, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time thou didſt ſay, we were a company of fools: ſuch admonitions were not given by the Apoſtles, but theſe words came from thy fallible ſpirit, for the ſpirit of truth ſaith, <hi>He that calleth his brother fool,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.2</note> 
               <hi>is in danger of hell fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the infallible ſpirit ſaith, <hi>Let no corrupt communication proceed out of your mouthes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.2 30.</note> 
               <hi>but ſuch as may Miniſter grace to the hearers;</hi> but thy ſpirit will ſay any thing, thy tongue is thy own.</p>
            <p>Judge now you that are his hearers, are you like to profit by ſuch a one that cannot refrain his tongue from ſpeaking evil, and ſuch are in the hereſie.</p>
            <p>Thou didſt ſay, he that was an heretick thou wouldſt reject, and thou dideſt bid me go away from thee, thou wouldeſt have nothing to do with me, nor ſpeak no more with me, when after that thou didſt ſpeak many words more to me, which I told thee of, and did ask thee, wherefore thou didſt do ſo, when thou ſaidſt thou would ſpeak no more to me: here was the lye found in thy mouth.</p>
            <p>And thou didſt bid me have a care of the Churches power, for what they bound in earth was bound in heaven; thou art under that Church power; but for the power of your Church, your curſe and your bleſſing, all is one, as was made manifeſt in <hi>Scotland,</hi> when our Army went into the Land, there was curſe upon curſe, excommunication one after another.</p>
            <p>See your Churches power, or rather your blindneſs, to curſe thoſe the Lord will bleſs, and did bleſs: your curſes, and theirs,<note place="margin">Num.</note> is like to <hi>Balaams</hi> curſes (all off one power) they are the inſtruments, as they are in your hands, of fooliſh ſhepherds, though Church-power I do own, and wo be to that that is under their cenſure, that muſt be given to Sathan, that the ſpirit may be ſaved in the day of the Lord, but this is done by the infallible ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:115359:19"/>
When you are rathered together,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4, 5</note> and my ſpirit with the power of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt to deliver ſuch a one unto Satan, for the deſtruction of the fleſh that the ſpirit may be ſaved in the day of the Lord. But <hi>Pauls</hi> infallible ſpirit is denyed by you, and your Churches cenſures denyed by me.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:115359:19"/>
            <head>The Babe in Chriſt growing up to a perfect man.<note place="margin">Heb. 5.13. Eph. 4.13.</note>
            </head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">He that hath the Son hath this witneſs in him.</note>THe hereſies that thou did caſt me our for, were theſe. 1. That I did hold perfection in this life. A ſtate of perfection I would have proved there was, and I did take the Bible ſo for to do, but thou didſt take it out of my hand, and did knock it many times together, as if thou hadſt not been thy ſelf, and would not ſuffer me for to ſpeak,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.6.</note> but thou ſaid thou would ſtand for the truth againſt all the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks in the world, and maintain it that there was no perfection in this life.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.47, 48, 49.</note> That which was given forth from the infallible ſpirit will prove it, that which is born of the fleſh is fleſh, and that which is born of the ſpirit, is ſpirit: the firſt man of the earth earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the ſecond man is the Lord from heaven: as is the earthly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.13.</note> ſuch are thoſe that are earthly, and as is the heavenly ſuch are they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that are heavenly, which were born not of blood,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 3.3.</note> nor of the will of man but of God; the firſt birth is of the earth and is earthly and ſhall never enter into the kingdom: except a man be born a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, he cannot ſee the kingdom of God, but being born again, not of corruptible ſeed, but of incorruptible ſeed by the word of God which liveth and abideth for ever; this is the new birth that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the new man; and this new man is created in righteouſneſs and holineſs after the ſimilitude of him that did create him,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23.</note> and this new man is perfect; yea know that whoſoever is born of God, ſinneth not, but he that is begotten of God, keepeth himſelf, and the wicked one reacheth him not. This is the new mans ſtate of perfection, which is the ſtate of life, and nothing that is not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſhall never enter the kingdom, no unclean thing ſhall enter, that which is not perfect is not clean:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.18</note> and here thou haſt ſhewed thy ſelf to be ignorant of the perfect ſtate of the Saints, and yet thou will ſay thy ſelf, there is a ſtate of death, and a ſtate of life: the ſtate of death is imperfection, there it lyeth; the ſtate of life is perfect, and, in perfection that lieth. And this was <hi>Pauls</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, and that which he did preach, warning every man, and teaching every man in all wiſdom, that he may preſent every man
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115359:20"/>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in Chriſt Jeſus,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1.28.</note> and this was the end of the ſending forth of the Miniſtery for the perfecting of the Saints. There are Babes in Chriſt; in their growth, and meaſure attained are the children of God, for they are begotten by the immortal ſeed of God, parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the Divine nature, which liveth and abideth for ever; there are young men in Chriſt, and there are fathers; and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the meaſure that every one hath attained, ſo let him walk: but the ſtate of all thoſe is a perfect ſtate,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.12, 13.</note> it is a ſtate of life, but the old man that is begotten by the will of man; is not perfect but he that is in Chriſt Jeſus is a new creature; old things are paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed away, and all things are become new. Here is cleanſing our ſelves from all filthineſs of the fleſh and ſpirit, perfecting holineſs in the fear of the Lord; this ſtate, this new birth is witneſſed by thoſe that know the Lord, though by you denyed and called he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie; this is the ſeed of God that cannot ſin; this is the perfect ſtate,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1.</note> this ſeed of God dwelleth in the Saints, this is their new birth from carnal to ſpiritual, &amp; the tranſlation from death to life: by this life they know the Lord, and by this life are joyned to the Lord, and he that is joyned to the Lord is one ſpirit with the Lord, and ſo the Church is called Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12. and is the temple of the Lord which is holy, and the Lord will dwell in them, and walk in them, and will be their God and they ſhall be his people: and for this cauſe we faint not,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16</note> but though our outward man periſh, yet the inward man is renewed day by day, which is the perfect man, Theſe are they that are not defiled with women, for they are Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, theſe are they that follow the Lamb whereſoever he goeth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.4, 5.</note> theſe were redeemed from among men, being the firſt fruites unto God and to the Lambe, and in their mouth was found no guile, for they are without fault before the throne,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 4.7.</note> there is no ſpot in them, they are all faire beloved of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Thou didſt tell me <hi>Paul</hi> did complain of a body of ſin all his life long. I told thee there was a time he did, &amp; there was a time he did witneſs the putting off the body of ſin, and thou didſt ſay to me he did not, and didſt tell me it was hereſie. See what the declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of truth ſaith againſt thy hereſie, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11. in whom ye are Circumciſed with the Circumciſion made without hands in put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off the body of the ſins of the fleſh by the circumciſion of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. <hi>chapter,</hi> verſ. 6. Knowing that the old man is cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified with him, that the body of ſin might be deſtroyed: for this end was the Son of God made manifeſt to deſtroy the works of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.8.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I did tell thee the Saints habitation was in God, thou didſt it deny, and didſt ſay it was a new word (to thee it is ſo) but the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible ſpirit ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 3.3, 4.</note> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.15, 16. whoſoever ſhall confeſs that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus is the Son of God, God dwelleth in him, and he in God, and he that dwelleth in God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 17.21</note> and God in him, where the Saints doth dwell, there is his habitation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:115359:20"/>
For ye ſee your calling brethren how that not many wiſe men af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fleſh, not many mighty, not many noble are called but God hath choſen the fooliſh things of the world to confound the wiſe, and God hath choſen the weak things of the world to confound the things that are mighty, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.26, 27.</p>
            <p>I would deſire thee if thou wilt anſwer any thing that is here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee ſaid, to anſwer it in plainneſs of ſpeech by writting or ſome other way, that I may know of it, and not to ſpeak in thy Pulpit againſt hereſie, but prove none; and if thou knoweſt any hereſie by me, that I now do hold, make it manifeſt, name what it is, and that day thou haſt a mind ſo for to do, ſend for me, do it not when I am abſent, and I ſhall give thee the hearing, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to ſuch things as thou ſhalt object againſt me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He that hath an ear to hear, let him hear what the ſpirit ſaith, he that overcometh ſhall not be hurt of the ſecond death,</hi> Rev. 2.11.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>John Payne</hi> Shoomaker, living in <hi>Biſhopſtarford.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
